{"tossups": [{"question": "One district in this city was dubbed \u201cElectric Town\u201d for its booming black market. Six island fortresses were built on the artificial island of Odaiba in this city, which may be reached through Rainbow Bridge. In 1960 in this city\u2019s Hibiya Hall, a nationalist stabbed a socialist politician on live TV; that hall is in this city\u2019s Chiyoda ward. For ten points, name this city where Frank Lloyd Wright\u2019s Imperial Hotel survived the 1923 Great Kanto earthquake.", "answer": "<b> Tokyo</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "One candidate for the Democratic nomination in this election year was a New Jersey senator who had played for the New York Knicks. The South Carolina primary in this year was won by a \u201ccompassionate conservative.\u201d This election was the last in which the Green Party nominated Ralph Nader for president; he was accused of causing a spoiler effect in this year. This election saw \u201changing chads\u201d cause a long recount in Florida ended by the Supreme Court. For ten points, name this election in which George W. Bush defeated Al Gore.", "answer": "Election of<b> 2000</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Infighting within this state led to the Battle of Bogesund, in which one side\u2019s leader perished on the frozen Lake Malaren. This state faced a rebellion by Erik Puke, who attempted to fulfill the goals of the earlier Engelbrekt rebellion. The second ruler of this state was Eric of Pomerania; his predecessor defeated Albrecht of Mecklenberg to form this state. A bloodbath caused by the Archbishop of Uppsala, along with the coronation of Gustav I of Sweden, greatly weakened this state, which was founded by Margaret I of Denmark. For ten points, name this medieval union of Norway, Sweden, and Denmark.", "answer": "<b> Kalmar</b> Union", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This figure is the alphabetically-prior namesake of a manifesto that inspired the Pugwash anti-WMD conference; that manifesto is named after this man and Bertrand Russell. David Ben-Gurion tried to make this man the first President of Israel, a post he refused. With Leo Szilard [zee-LAR], this scientist wrote a letter to FDR that inspired the Manhattan Project. For ten points, name this scientist who formulated general and special relativity.", "answer": "Albert<b> Einstein</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This war was prompted by the death of John Sassamon, and its northern front was called the First Abenaki War. Josiah Winslow led the victorious forces in one of this war\u2019s battles, the Great Swamp Fight. Mary Rowlandson wrote her captivity narrative about this war which was ended by the Treaty of Casco Bay. This war, which destroyed the Narragansett, was named for the son of Massasoit who had sheltered the Pilgrims 50 years earlier. For ten points, name this war in which the New England colonies defeated a namesake Native American leader.", "answer": "King<b> Philip\u2019s</b> War (or<b> Metacomet</b>\u2019s War; accept equivalents like \u201crebellion\u201d for war)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "One composer from this country wrote a series of nine suites that fuse Bach-style Baroque harmonies to this nation\u2019s folk music. A drought-stricken ranch in this nation\u2019s<em> sert\u02dcao</em> is the setting of Glauber Rocha\u2019s film<em> Black God, White Devil</em>, a landmark film in a movement inspired from across the Atlantic by French New Wave called Cinema Novo. Heitor Villa-Lobos is the foremost composer of this country\u2019s classical style. For ten points, name this country whose government hired Lucio Costa and Oscar Niemeyer to plan a new capital city, replacing Rio de Janeiro.", "answer": "<b> Brazil</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Film"}, {"question": "The prices charged by these companies were the subject of Regulation Q. In the 1980s and early 90s, a \u201ccrisis\u201d caused over a thousand of one variant of these companies to fail. The Gramm-Leach-Bliley Act repealed one law that mandated separation of two types of these companies; that law, the Glass-Steagall Act, separated their \u201ccommercial\u201d and \u201cinvestment\u201d types. For ten points, name these financial companies that were bailed out in the 2008 financial crisis, modern examples of which include JPMorganChase and Citigroup.", "answer": "<b> bank</b>s (accept types of banks like investment<b> bank</b>s, commercial<b> bank</b>s, etc.; prompt on \u201cfinancial services\u201d and other generic answers; prompt on other types of financial companies like\u201cInsurance,\u201d \u201cBrokers,\u201d etc.) Page 2", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Economics"}, {"question": "A nominally neutral party in this war was led by Teganissorens, who concluded negotiations with the losing side\u2019s commander, Vaudreuil. Aggrieved losers from this war fought Dummer\u2019s War about a decade later. The losing side flauted the treaty ending this war by reconstructing Fort Niagara in 1722. This war\u2019s loser retained Cape Breton, but was forced to cede Saint Kitts as well as Newfoundland and Acadia. Partly fought over the patronage of the Iroquois, this conflict was ended by the Treaty of Utrecht, as it is the North American phase of the Thirty Years\u2019 War. For ten points, name this war, named in America for the final Stuart ruler.", "answer": "<b> Queen Anne</b>\u2019s War (accept<b> Thirty Years\u2019</b> War until mentioned)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "One politician from this country insisted that Jan B\u00a8ohmermann stand trial for a poem that implied he has sex with goats and watches child pornography. That politician shuttered the main opposition paper in this country,<em> Zaman</em>. This country shot down a Russian Su-24 after it allegedly encroached on its airspace, and it reached an agreement with the EU where it would receive billions in aid in exchange for taking Syrian refugees from Greece. Recep Erdogan is president of, for ten points, what country ruled from Ankara?", "answer": "Republic of<b> Turkey</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "Seven African-American strikebreakers in this industry were killed along with four of their guards in the 1898 Battle of Virden. The shooting of Baldwin-Felts agents in the Matewan Massacre led to a battle between 3000 strikebreakers and 10,000 workers in this industry at Blair Mountain; those workers were supported by<em> Mother Jones</em>. It\u2019s not oil, but a company owned by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. killed around 20 workers in this industry in Colorado. The fall of natural gas prices has caused numerous bankruptcies in this industry, whose workers often develop black lung. For ten points, name this industry, common in West Virginia, that extracts a solid fossil fuel.", "answer": "<b> coal mining</b> (prompt on mining)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The state National Guard joined in this massacre, in which two dozen people were killed.", "answer": "<b> Ludlow</b> Massacre Page 3", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In one work in this set, an old woman wields a knife in defense of a woman getting raped. This set was influenced by a set of works by Jacques Callot which depicts scenes from the Thirty Years War. The only identifiable character in this set of works is Agustina of Aragon, who is shown manning cannons in the Siege of Zaragoza. These engravings critique politics following Ferdinand VII\u2019s return to power. For ten points, name this set of 82 prints created by Francisco Goya that depict the miseries of the Peninsular War.", "answer": "the<b> Disasters of War</b> series", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "The Yorkist pretender Richard de la Pole died during this battle. Another commander killed in this battle, Francois de Lorraine, commanded a group of Landsknechts known as the Black Band. The losing ruler in this battle is misquoted as saying \u201cAll is lost save honor\u201d in a letter to his mother Louise of Savoy. Charles de Lannoy commanded the winning side in this battle, where one ruler was forced to give up his country\u2019s claim to Italy in the Treaty of Madrid. For ten points, name this 1525 battle in which Francis I was captured by forces under Charles V, fought just south of Milan.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Pavia</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "In the 16th century, Wang Zi combined his merchant business with this profession, establishing himself on the Goto Islands. Cheung Po Tsai became a member of this profession after being kidnapped by Cheng I, who himself was a member of this profession. Gwanggaeto the Great defeated the Wokou, Japanese members of this profession. After the death of her husband, Ching Shih took control of a large group of these people. In this role, Cai Qian led numerous raids on Taiwan and defeated the Qing [CHING] Navy at Wenzhou. For ten points, name this illicit profession of sea-based thievery.", "answer": "<b> pirates</b> (accept similar answers such as<b> raiders</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This man signed his articles as Raro and Eusebius in the<em> Neue Zeitschrift f\u00a8ur Musik</em>. This man wrote a set of works that depicts a hobby-horse and a game of Blind Man\u2019s Bluff and dedicated his<em> Kreislerania</em> to Chopin. The composer of three Romances for violin and piano married this man in 1837, 13 years before their trip to Cologne Cathedral inspired part of his<em> Rhenish</em> Symphony. For ten points, name this composer of<em> Scenes from Childhood</em> who married Clara Wieck [VEEK].", "answer": "Robert<b> Schumann</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "A group made of university students that opposed this man lynched Imperial Minister of War Theodor Franz and was called the Academic Legion. The March Revolution repealed a set of laws issued by this man that were passed after the murder of the writer August von Kotzebue. The incendiary speeches of Lajos Kossuth partially caused this man\u2019s resignation and temporary exile. For ten points, name this reactionary statesman who fled Austria during the Revolutions of 1848, ending this man\u2019s namesake \u201cage\u201dthat began with the Congress of Vienna.", "answer": "Prince Klemens Wenzel von<b> Metternich</b> (accept Clement Wenceslas Lothar von<b> Metternich</b>-Winneburg-Beilstein)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>After this disaster, Senegalese president Abdoulaye Wade offered its victims free land. Missionaries from the New Life Children\u2019s Refuge were accused of kidnapping for attempting to arrange for the adoption of children affected by this crisis. Cholera outbreaks after this</b> <b>disaster were blamed on (+)</b> <b>Nepalese peacekeepers. Rapper Wyclef Jean tried to run in</b> <b>Nepalese peacekeepers. Rapper Wyclef Jean tried to run in</b> <b>the presidential election held in the year of this disaster, and (*)</b> <b>the presidential election held in the year of this disaster, and (*)</b> Michel Martelly became president a year later. For ten points, name this natural disaster that destroyed Port-au-Prince in 2010.", "answer": "2010<b> Haiti</b>an<b> earthquake</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b>The Foursquare Church was founded in this city by a preacher who later disappeared from a beach off one of this city\u2019s Western neighborhoods. That lady preacher from this city was allegedly kidnapped to Mexico in 1926 and was named Aimee (+) Semple McPherson. This city saw the founding of the modern Pentecostal movement by William J. Seymour in 1906 as host of the Azusa Street Revival. In the present day, Cardinal Roger Mahoney leads this city\u2019s Catholics, who form the (*) </b> largest archdiocese in the United States. For ten points, name this West Coast city where preachers often try to convert Hollywood stars.", "answer": "<b> L</b>os<b> A</b>ngeles", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>The Karta of Kabi revolted against a ruler of this state whose doom was spelled by the death of his general, Kanfari Omar. The</b><em><b> Tarikh al-Fattash</b></em><b> and the</b><em><b> Tarikh al-Sudan</b></em><b> are the</b> <b>main sources of this state\u2019s history, which includes its victory in the Battle of (+)</b> <b>Anfao</b> <b>and its succession by the Dendi Kingdom after Ahmad al-Mansur defeated it in the Battle of Tondibi. The greatest ruler of this empire had a spiky (*) </b> pyramid for a tomb, and this empire was founded in Sunni Ali\u2019s revolt out of Gao. For ten points, name this West African empire of Askia the Great that absorbed much of the weakened Mali empire.", "answer": "<b> Songhai</b> Empire", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>Richard FitzNeal advised this ruler, who printed the \u201cShort Cross\u201d penny. This ruler signed the treaty of Windsor, which placed Rory O\u2019Connor on the throne of Ireland. He</b> <b>ascended to the throne following the signing of the Treaty of (+)</b> <b>Wallingford and the end</b> <b>of the Anarchy, and he attempted to curb papal power in the Constitution of (*)</b> Clarendon. The \u201cGreat Revolt\u201d against this man was led by Eleanor of Aquitaine and his son Richard. His knights notably killed the Archbishop of Canterbury, Thomas a Becket. For ten points, name this first Plantagenet king of England.", "answer": "<b> Henry II</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>One commander in this battle stationed himself at the easily targeted Sultan Ibrahim building, knowing that the other side wasn\u2019t brave enough to blow it up. Force Z was destroyed prior to this battle. The Alexandra (+) Hospital massacre took place during this battle, where ANZAC troops were led by Gordon Bennett. After losing the Kranji River, a meeting at Fort Canning convinced one side to surrender, leading to what (*) </b> Winston Churchill called the \u201cworst disaster\u201d and \u201clargest capitulation\u201d of British soldiers in history. Arthur Percival was the loser of, for ten points, what February 1942 battle for control of a major Allied base off the Malay Peninsula?", "answer": "Battle of<b> Singapore</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This author notably made a distinction between those who are slaves according</b> <b>to law and those who are slaves by nature. This author described six types of</b> <b>constitutions, illustrating how (+) tyranny, oligarchy, and democracy are perversions</b> <b>of royalty, aristocracy, and constitutional government. This author described the role</b> <b>of (*)</b> catharsis in a work about tragedy. For ten points, name this author of<em> Politics</em> and<em> Poetics</em> who founded the Lyceum and was a student of Plato.", "answer": "<b> Aristotle</b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {}], "bonuses": []}